Guide to the Prohibition Collection 1977.127
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Prohibition collection
1893-1942
1893-1921
Brooklyn Historical Society
Prohibition Party (U.S.)
Hilliard, George B.
1977.127
0.8 Linear Feet in one document box, one oversize box, and one box of cabinet cards
The Prohibition Collection contains temperance periodicals, publications, correspondence, photographs, lecture invitations, campaign material, and newspaper clippings, 1893-1942, relating to the Prohibition movement in the U.S. and in New York State and City in particular. This material provides a look at this American political movement from the local level in New York and Kings Counties. The bulk of the material was donated in 1932 by George B. Hilliard, who was involved in the Prohibition movement for decades and was a county organizer and executive committee member for the Prohibition County Committee of New York. Some of the items date from 1933 to 1942 and their provenance cannot be established.
Oversize OS-25
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Historical Note
The American Prohibition movement began in the mid-1800's and grew in influence and popularity until it achieved its greatest victory in 1918 with the passage of the 18th Amendment, which stated: "After one year from the ratification of this article, the manufacture, sale, or transportation of intoxicating liquors within, the importation thereof into, or the exportation thereof from the United States and all territory subject to the jurisdiction thereof for beverage purposes is hereby prohibited." 1
Never universally popular and a heralded example of the difficulty of legislating morality via the U.S. Constitution, the 18th Amendment was repealed by passage of the 21st Amendment in 1933. The movement in New York fielded candidates for mayor of New York City and state governor, and a national party defined an issue platform and fielded candidates for President and Vice President of the U.S.. The enthusiasm with which the Prohibitionists embraced their cause can be seen in a quote from Clarence Elwyn Pitts, chairman of the Prohibition Central Committee in New York State, to a fellow Prohibitionist: "If we build wisely and well; sink personal differences into the commonweal; and plan carefully, we shall inaugurate a system of organization and development of work which will result in a mighty forward movement all over the state." 2
Bibliography
1. http://www.gpoaccess.gov/constitution/pdf/con029.pdf. Accessed January 18, 2006.
2. Clarence Elwyn Pitts, in a letter to John Berry, December 12, 1910. Prohibition Collection, ArMs 1977.127, Box 1, Folder 4, Brooklyn Historical Society.
The American Prohibition movement began in the mid-1800's and grew in influence and popularity until it achieved its greatest victory in 1918 with the passage of the 18th Amendment, which stated: "After one year from the ratification of this article, the manufacture, sale, or transportation of intoxicating liquors within, the importation thereof into, or the exportation thereof from the United States and all territory subject to the jurisdiction thereof for beverage purposes is hereby prohibited."
Never universally popular and a heralded example of the difficulty of legislating morality via the U.S. Constitution, the 18th Amendment was repealed by passage of the 21st Amendment in 1933. The movement in New York fielded candidates for mayor of New York City and state governor, and a national party defined an issue platform and fielded candidates for President and Vice President of the U.S.. The enthusiasm with which the Prohibitionists embraced their cause can be seen in a quote from Clarence Elwyn Pitts, chairman of the Prohibition Central Committee in New York State, to a fellow Prohibitionist: "If we work and plan wisely and well,—without prejudice,—& for the benefit of the entire state,—we can soon develop a fighting organization in every assembly dist.,—& within 2 yr., in every election district,—& begin a mighty forward movement."
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in 7 series: Series 1. Administrative Documents, Series 2. Campaign Materials, Series 3. Clippings, Series 4. Correspondence, Series 5. Events Materials, Series 6. Literature, Series 7. Maps, Photographs and Works on Paper. Within each series, folders are organized alphabetically by title and materials in each folder are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents Note
The Prohibition Collection documents the activities of the New York State Prohibition Party as well as many other organizations that were active in the prohibition movement in New York City and Brooklyn, including the Prohibition Parties of New York and Kings Counties, the Woman's Christian Temperance League, and the Young People's Prohibition League. While the collection covers the years 1893-1942, the bulk of materials in the collection covers roughly the mid 1890s through the 1910s when the Prohibition movement in the United States was at its most active.
Included in the collection are administrative records of the New York State Prohibition Party; Prohibition literature, including periodicals and informational booklets; campaign materials, including brochures and leaflets; events materials, such as event programs and photographs of events; maps of the National Prohibition Park in Staten Island, as well as photographic and engraved portraits of prominent figures of the New York Prohibitionist movement.
Immediate Source of Acquisiton
Donated by George B. Hilliard in 1932.
Photograph Records
Item-level description and digital versions of images from the collection are available for searching via the online image database.
Photographs; Prohibition |z United States; United States |x Politics and government; Engravings; Temperance |z United States |v Periodicals; Social movements |z United States; Correspondence; Temperance |z United States; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.) |v Maps; National Prohibition Park (New York, N.Y.); Maps; New York County Prohibition Committee; Prohibition Party (U.S.); Hilliard, George B.; Kings County Prohibition Committee (Kings County, N.Y.); Woman's Christian Temperance Union; Brooklyn Young Peoples Prohibition League
- Series 1 - Administrative Documents, 1896-1913
  - New York State Prohibition Party, 1896-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series 2 - Campaign Materials, 1892-1931
  - Brochures and Leaflets, 1892-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 3 - Clippings, 1900-1942
  - Clippings, 1900-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 4 - Correspondence, 1900-1911
  - Correspondence, 1900-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series 5 - Events Materials, 1895-1921
  - Kings County Prohibition Committee, 1906-1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1895-1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New York County Prohibitionists, 1897-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Young People's Prohibition League, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 6 - Literature, 1896-1942
  - Booklets, 1896-1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Periodicals, 1899-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 7 - Maps, Photographs and Works on Paper, circa 1890-1910
  - Maps - National Prohibition Park, Staten Island, circa 1890-1897 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs - Events and Campaigns, circa 1890-1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographic Portraits - Cabinet Cards, circa 1890-1919 (Box Cabinet Cards 1)
  - Photographic Portraits - Groups, c. 1890s-1910s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographic Portraits - Individuals, c. 1890s-1910s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Works on Paper - Engraved Portraits, circa 1890-1919 (Box 1, Folder 15)